Hello friends and welcome back to True
Health Tuesdays. I am so glad you're
here. I am so glad to be back with you
and I'm very very excited about today's
topic. Cancer is actually a very
personal topic for me.
because it's been in my family, lots of
family members with cancer. My husband
was uh diagnosed with cancer a couple of
years ago. And I will tell you all about
what we did with his case. Today though,
we're going to talk about what I
promised in the title, which is um
causes cancer. What causes cancer? So,
I'm going to go straight to that. But
first of all, I want to talk about well,
I want to tell you that first of all, I
want to give you a disclaimer. This is
not going to be uh uh any type of uh
diagnosis. We're not going to give
anybody's a treatment or anything like
that. So, I just want to let you know
this is educational. So, that's the
first disclaimer. This is uh don't take
this as any kind of treatment or medical
advice.
Second disclaimer that will be mostly
for all my SDA friends will be a
spiritual
disclaimer and I that just like the
first uh program that we had together
two weeks ago I want to let you know
that with all my
presentations this will be 100% in
accordance to the Bible and spirit of
prophecy. I will always tell you that at
the very beginning because that's how
important I think it is to be in harmony
with Bible and spirit of prophecy. So
rule number one Isaiah 8:20 and uh you
already know it but I just want to just
in case uh somebody is here for the
first time to the law and the testimony
if they do not speak according to this
word it is because there's no light in
them. And as we know, well, many of you
already know, many of you might not, but
how we interpret this uh Bible verse is
that the word
um the law and the testimony, we
interpret it like this, the law being
the Bible and the testimony being uh the
spirit of prophecy. I added one more
thing here uh because I think we live in
very uh important times right now. I
don't know how many of you agree with
me. We are living in extremely
uh interesting times to say the least.
And uh um
Revelation is a very relevant book right
now. And uh interestingly very relevant
for us as the church. Uh Revelation
12:17 says, "And the dragon was enraged
with the woman." Who's the woman, by the
way?
Those of you who are connected, you
might want to put in the chat, who do
you think the woman
is? I know who I think the woman is. I
think that's us, the church. The dragon
being the enemy of the church. The
dragon was enraged with the woman and
went to make war against the rest of her
offspring. Who do you think that
is? and uh those who keep the
commandments of God and have the
testimony of Jesus. Therefore, there
Yes, thank you,
Don.
Uh the enemy, the dragon is at war with
us. At war with us, those who keep the
commandments of God and have the
testimony of Jesus. Therefore, we need
to be more than ever more than ever
knowledgeable of everything to do with
both spiritual things and health things.
Um, so we know what the testimony of
Jesus is because it says in the same
book, Revelation, but a little bit, you
know, uh, more towards the end of the
book, it says that revelation, uh, it
says that the testimony of Jesus is the
spirit of prophecy. So just like I said
last uh presentation, I recommend just
as a starter uh these two books just to
get you started. Ministry of healing and
councils of diet and food. Uh and number
two is the importance of uh scientific
evidence. Uh, and what I didn't say last
time is the bottom the bottom of this um
pyramid if you will is uh the kind of
the lowest quality of of scientific
evidence and that's opinion. And uh if
you hear just people telling you
anecdotes and stories, that's the lowest
quality of evidence. The highest quality
of evidence is reviews and uh meta
analysis. So if you hear scientific
evidence, make sure it's good quality.
And
um and going on on that, by the way,
spirit of prophecy. So here are the
quotes that I showed you last week that
uh the book Christian education says the
knowledge of science of all kinds is
power. The knowledge of science of all
kinds is power. In other words, we're
not in some kind of battle against
science. And then the other one says um
a practical knowledge of science of
human life is necessary in order to
glorify God in our bodies. So I don't
want to you know stay on this too long
because we already saw them last week. I
want to go ahead and go to our um to our
topic for the day. I'm going to go ahead
and skip this one because we saw it last
week too. So we're going to talk about
cancer today. Cancer is a very scary
word. I know it was scary for me when I
heard the first
time. Um well, you know, I heard it many
times in my family, my
grandpa, my aunt, uh my my mom's sister,
very young age, uh many people in my
family. But when it was my husband,
that's when it really really that's when
that's when it was more personal. You
know what I mean? Like when it's your
immediate family, it could be your
husband, your your child, your parent,
that's when it really touches you. What
do you think when you hear the C word?
What do you think? Put in the chat what
comes to mind when you hear the word
cancer. Does it scare you? Does it does
it feel different for you when you hear
the word cancer than when you hear I
don't know
diabetes or when you hear the word heart
disease? Does it feel different? Tell
me. Put it in the chat if you if it
feels different to you because for me it
did. When I when when I walked into the
um to the recovery room, my husband was
recovering from a colonoscopy because,
you know, he woke up basically. He was
put to sleep when or he was put asleep
when he had the colonoscopy and and I I
walked in and he just looked at me. He
just gave me that look like, yes, it was
cancer. And I was like, it just feels so
terrible. It just it just feels
horrible.
So I don't know how you know if you had
that experience if you have share share
with us uh how it's felt for you if it
feels any different but for me it did
it's a scary word I think um yeah it
just it has a different feel than any
other disease I think just a scary thing
it's just it's the
uncertainty what's going to happen where
does it come from what causes it you
know we just don't know it's just the
uncertainty it's scary but anyway way.
There's cancer statistics uh that are
pretty scary, too. Person born the 19 in
1990 has four times the risk of
developing cancer as someone born in
1950. Uh cancer has been going up, as
you probably know, especially certain
types of
cancer. Uh but um there's certain types
of cancer have been going up a lot. Um,
but this is worldwide, not just in the
US, but younger generations. This is
scary that younger people or it's
happening at younger and younger ages. I
want to say
um there's 14 sites uh that have been
increasing lately. Colorctal cancer is
the one that's been increasing a lot
lately in younger and younger ages. I
don't know if you've read this in the
news. Have you put it put it in the chat
if you have been seeing this in the news
lately how it's been happening at
younger and younger ages but colurectal
cancer colon cancer has been really been
diagnosed at younger younger ages but
these are all the other ones that have
been also uh in been increasing
lately and um the digestive system h why
can that be happening why do you think
digestive system. Oh, leading
hypothesis. Do you see why? Do you see
what the leading hypothesis is here? Due
to what now? Obesity. Well, that's one
of the um hypothesis anyway.
Inflammation. H I wonder
why. All right.
Well, this is something that very
important that I want to start off
with the three stages of cancer.
Not the not the same thing as when you
actually are diagnosed with cancer.
That's
different. What I'm talking about here
when I talk about the three stages of
cancer is the three stages of cancer
development. How does it
start? Why does it start? All right. So
that's what we're going to talk about
because this is very important. Um later
we'll see why. But how does cancer
initiate in the body and then how does
it
spread? That's what we're going to talk
about. So look at these number one, two,
and three. Okay? Number one, two and
three. Number one is initiation. Number
one, initiation.
Number two, this is very important
because I want you to remember this
later. Number two is
promotion.
Promotion. And number
three is what now? Progression. Okay,
these are three different things that
need to happen in order for cancer to
eventually then be diagnosed. All right.
So, what's initiation? And then we see
three different
um potential
initiators of cancer. Now I want to say
something because I'm not going to talk
about this very much because you see
things here that you probably already
heard a lot like chemicals, radiation,
but then you hear here you see viruses
and you're like what viruses?
What? Well, it turns out that 20% of
cancers are caused by
viruses like HIV. Well, that you that
okay. Oh, yeah.
HIV. AIDS, right? Like eventually HIV
causes AIDS if it's not treated
properly. HPV, EBV, oh, COVID 19. What?
Yeah, it turns out SARS
KV2. that now that it's been around
actually this is the most widespread
virus actually now we found out that
does cause cancer but there's a bunch of
viruses that actually do cause cancer
and interestingly I just I just want to
let you know this is a parenthesis right
now because we're going to talk about
other things but just as a parenthesis
it turns
out that Ellen White in that book that I
told you I hope you're reading it it's
called Ministry of Healing wrote
something pretty interesting
Way back more than 100 years ago, people
are continually eating flesh that is
filled with tuberculus and cancerous
germs.
Germs, tuberculosis, cancer, and other
fatal diseases are thus
communicated. And people are like, "Ah,
she doesn't know what she's talking
about." People are like
laughing. This lady doesn't know what
she's talking about. Cancer doesn't come
from germs.
It turns out now over a hundred years
later, oops, she was right. How did she
know? Well, anyway, that's for another
day because today we're going to
concentrate on the other causes really.
Um, we're going to talk first talk first
of all about some of the chemical causes
of cancer because these are quite
avoidable. These are the top chemical
carcinogens.
As you probably know,
tobacco number one
uh carcinogen probably in the world.
Thank goodness it has been going down in
the United States. Uh the rates of
tobacco use have gone down dramatically.
You know, I remember as a child, you
might not believe me, but when I was a
kid, my dad used to send me to buy
cigarettes for him. I don't know if this
happened to you. This was allowed in the
1980s in the country where I lived. My
dad would give me money and I would go
buy cigarettes for him. He like, "Okay,
here. Uh, no big
deal." Uh, and everybody smoked back
then, you know. I live I lived in a
house surrounded by secondhand smoke. I
breathed it in all the time. My lungs
are probably not that great because my
dad smoked in the house and it was
allowed
everywhere. So, that was the thing.
Thank goodness that has changed. Oh,
that's it's just kids wouldn't even
believe how we grew up. Kids
nowadays. Uh yeah, you even in uh even
in uh airplanes. I remember those days.
So, I don't know if you remember those
days, but it was terrible. So, thank
goodness the air is much cleaner
nowadays in that sense. But tobacco has
thousands. Uh nicotine, tobacco,
cigarettes have thousands of chemicals
that cause cancer. FYI. So if you know
anyone who smokes, please tell them
about this. But number two, do you see
that one
alcohol? My dad, my dad, I can tell you
stories. Uh my dad was one of those
people who had this little cup of red
wine every night. He had been an
Adventist, FYI. But then, you know, he
had too many vices, too many um
addictions. And um I would call him say,
"Hey, Dad, how you doing? What are you
Oh, I'm drinking my little cup of wine.
I'm like,
"Dad, you know this." You know, the
Bible says, you know, alcohol. Oh, but
the doctor
said, doctor said the wine is good for
your
heart. Come on. And the doctors were
saying that back in the 1990s and it was
true. The doctors were saying
that. Well,
now I think they're eating their words
hopefully
because now the doctors that are
responsible will tell you that the only
safe amount of alcohol to drink. Do you
know what you know what that amount is?
Do you
know? Those of you who know, please put
it in the chat. What is the safe amount
of alcohol to drink?
What is What is it? What is the safe
amount of alcohol you can drink every
day? What's What's the safe amount?
What's the threshold? Do you know what
it
is?
Zero. There's no safe amount of alcohol
you can drink that will not cause any
damage in your
body. One drink a day will already
increase your likelihood of cake. Thank
you, Durk. Thank you very much. Yes,
zero. That's the right amount. No amount
of alcohol is safe. No, nothing. Zero.
That's the right answer because one
drink a day will elevate the loo the
risk of cancer by 15% in women uh for
breast cancer. So zero is the right
amount. And sure people well what about
moderate? Okay. Well moderate amount of
poison in your liver I guess if that's
what you want. I can't tell you any
better because any amount of cancer, any
amount of alcohol will affect your
liver. That's that's it. I can't I you
know I can't defend even one drink a
day. I can't because it's poisonous.
It's it's it will affect your liver no
matter what. Even if small
amounts. That's what they say. So it is
a carcinogen. It's a carcinogen. But
we're going to talk about foods today.
Zero is indeed the right amount. Thank
you very much. show you all of you guys.
But what about the other toxins? Oh my
goodness, there's so much stuff out
there. Oh, there is so much stuff out
there. But I'm going to tell you why.
None of this is all that important.
Okay, but we have to acknowledge though,
there's plastics, there's
pesticides, there's, you know, I don't
know, in the air, all kinds of smog and
stuff and lead. And by the way, fish,
there's another
one. People tell me, "Well, what about
fish?" You know, that's that's the kind
of meat. You know, they say that it's
not that bad,
but you want me to tell you what I think
about fish. You want me to? Maybe I
shouldn't. I don't want to offend
anyone.
Okay, I'll tell you. Okay, please
forgive me. I will tell you what I think
about fishing because people say, "Well,
Jesus ate fish." Yeah. 2,000 years
ago. 2,000 years ago, you can walk to a
lake, a river, the ocean. There was no
mercury. Yeah. Thank you.
Re, yes, biomagnification is the right
word. You can walk to the ocean. There
was no mercury, no other chemicals, no
um all
these things agricultural and uh all
these uh all this waste
from industries, all kinds of stuff that
today is there. All these forever
chemicals. There were no chemicals 2,000
years ago, but today they're
biomagnified. Yes. Because the little uh
fish get all this um toxins into their
body. Then the medium-sized fish eat the
small fish and the bigger fish eat the
medium and the bigger fish and so on and
so forth. You eat the bigger fish and
you're getting tons of toxins. Fish is
the number one as far as
diet, number one source of most
chemicals and plastics.
Fish has nanoplastics like you would not
believe. But also plastic bottles have
plastics. The water in the plastic
bottles. I would say try to avoid
plastics as much as you can. So all of
these things. Okay. Yes. They're
everywhere. So people are like, you
know, people have this sometimes this
defeist attitude like everything kills
us nowadays. Everything gives us cancer.
So let's just give up. Let's just eat
burgers all day. No, it's not like that.
And I'll tell you why, but later. So,
keep that thought in your mind. Why is
it not like that? Let's not just say
that everything kills us. But
today, we are going to talk a little bit
about Well, what about food?
Huh? Do you think there are
foods that might have
certain things that initiate cancer?
Because we talked about initiate.
Remember when we talked about number
three, the three things, number one,
initiator,
initiation, number two, promotion,
number three, progression. So we're
talking about here number one,
initiation of cancer. What does that
mean? That means damage to the cells. So
these toxins that we were just talking
about, the toxins in cigarettes, the
toxins in alcohol, the toxins in
chemicals, radiation, all these things,
what do they do? They cause damage in
cells in the DNA, in the the genes
inside of your cells, in the nucleus of
your cells. That's where your DNA is.
They cause damage to that those genes.
And those damaged genes when the cells
start to replicate those damaged genes
then are also replicated. And so these
damaged cells then start to replicate
and that's how cancer then start because
these are damaged cells and then they
have this flaw in them that then allows
them to continue to grow without
stopping. Thank you. re initiation. Oh,
pollution. That's actually promotion.
The second one, initiation, promotion,
and progression. Thank you very much.
So, someone said processed foods. Thank
you. Yes. Oh my goodness. We have so
much to talk about. So, I'm just going
to I'm just going to get started. So,
what about food? Do you think there are
foods that might cause hear me out
initiation? Are there foods that might
damage our DNA? That's what I'm talking
about here. Because yeah, there are
foods that might clog our arteries, that
might cause what we talked about two
weeks ago, uh, insulin
resistance, but what about damage our
cells, damage our DNA? You know what I'm
talking
about? Cancer, initiate
cancer. What do you
think? Well, I'm going to tell you what
I learned from a really, really good
book. I don't know how many of you have
read this book. I have the old edition
somewhere. I don't know what I did with
it. I had it just a minute ago and then
I bought this newer edition because it
has additional chapters. So, I have both
editions, the old one and the new one.
So, this is from T. Colin Campbell who
is a researcher in nutrition. He's not a
medical doctor. He's one of those PhD
doctors
uh who's a researcher and he you know in
the 1950s he was one of those uh
nutrition researchers who thought that
milk was like a miracle from God. Oo the
milk is just wonderful. Uh he well he
came from a family who had like uh
ranches. So, of course, he supported
milk and uh animal foods. And so, he
thought protein, animal protein was the
best because you can grow, have muscles,
all this stuff, and just grow better.
And it turns out when he was a young
researcher, he went to the
Philippines because there was a lot of
liver cancer at the time in the
Philippines. And he had this, you know,
hypothesis in the mind already. he had
formed an idea that okay well it's
probably the poor children who have the
cancer uh in the liver because he
thought well at the time it was already
known that there's this very
very toxic
uh compound in peanuts that have gotten
moldy so peanuts that are kept in very
humid environments where they get mold
they have this toxin called aphotoxin
toxin in the mold. It's very
carcinogenic, extremely toxic. So he
thought, well, that's a poor country
over there. So they probably keep the
peanuts in um probably in places that
are not very well insulated or whatever.
They're probably kept in very, you know,
in uh in rooms or areas where they're
not very well clean or whatever. So they
have mold and so they have aphlotoxins.
So these poor children who can't eat
meat, oh poor kids, they can't afford
the meat or the milk or cheese or what
have you. They have to eat peanuts that
are bad. So then they are the ones who
are getting the cancer. That's was his
theory. So he got to the Philippines.
Oops. His was wrong. It wasn't the poor
children who were getting the liver
cancer. It was the affluent children who
were getting the liver cancer. That blew
away his theory completely. What? How is
it possible that kids are eating the
better foods, the the
meat, the
dairy? How is it that they're getting
cancer if they're good eating the good
foods? And the children who are eating
the
peanuts, how is it that they're not
getting the liver cancer? It doesn't
make any sense.
Well, so then he went back to the US
Cornell University and he started doing
some laboratory experiments with
rats and he gave them
aphletoxin, very toxic, very
carcinogenic
toxin. But he separated in them these
two groups of rats into groups. One, he
gave them a high protein diet.
and that the other group a low protein
diet to see which ones are going to get
the cancer. Guess what
happened? You want to know? Here's what
happened. Oh, I'm sorry. Here's what
happened. The low protein group had very
low
uh precursor cancer cell precursor
development. In other words, the group
that was eating very low protein were
hardly getting any cancer
development. But the rats that were
eating 20% protein, look at what's
happening. Do you see what's
happening? These rats are eating the
good protein as he was as he thought at
the moment. Right? These are these are
the rats eating the good protein. Why
are they getting all the
cancer? Does not make sense. He
thought, "What the heck?" And then he
repeated the same experiment with
mice. Do you think he got any different
uh results?
Nope. These mice were not getting
aphletoxin. These mice were uh mice that
had a virus that
causes liver cancer.
Same thing. He divided them in groups.
In this case, in this case, he had a a
control group right here. And the other
groups, he gave them high amounts
of
protein, low amount, medium amount of
protein, and low amount of protein. So,
high, medium, low. The dark you see
right here, this is straight from the
book, by the way, you guys. This is
straight from the book. You'll see this
exact picture in the book. The dark you
see right here,
cancer. This is the high protein
22%. Do you see any dark here? This is
the 6%. Do you see it? Do you see any
cancer in the pro in the low protein
group? The all the all the mice here
have the same virus that causes cancer.
They all had the same initiator. That's
what I'm trying to tell you guys. They
all had the same initiator. Just like
with the rats, the rats had all the same
initiator. You see what I'm saying? They
all had the same very toxic initiator of
cancer. They were all exposed to the
same
toxin. here. They're all exposed to the
same virus that causes
cancer, but not all of them
developed. Number two, you see why these
number these three steps are so
important? Because there's number one,
initiation, damage to the cells, but
number two is
promotion. You see the difference here?
You can initiate
cancer, but all of a
sudden the step number two is not
happening in
everyone, at least in the rats and the
mice. We haven't gotten to the people
yet. This is just all in the
lab. But do you see what's happening? I
hope you're getting what I'm trying to
say. So anyway, low protein, no dark
spots. medium protein, a little bit,
high protein, all kinds of dark spots.
And then they're like, "What? This is
like zero and 100, like so much
difference here. It's like day and
night. Let's just flip them. Let's see
what happens if we flip
them." You know what happened if when
they flipped them? The little mice that
had no cancer, what do you think
happened? Boom. Cancer showed up.
And the ones that had the
cancer stopped
growing. It's almost as if you had a
switch that you can turn on and
off. They all had the initiation.
Remember this. They all were exposed to
cancer, but it didn't develop all the
time. It didn't it didn't get to number
two. What was the difference? Courtney,
thank you, Courtney.
The difference was animal protein.
Animal protein is like the switch like
turn it on and
off. Weird, right? It's weird. Strange
concept. By the way, the protein that he
used, here's a picture of uh Dr.
Campbell. Here's the the uh the book.
That's the first uh that's how the first
um edition looks. The protein they used,
if you noticed, if you were paying
attention to the to the captions, the
protein they used happened to be
casein. Casein. What's casing? Oh, here
it is. It says right here. Makes up 87%
of
what? Cow's milk. I think he I think I
told you this last time that milk has
two kinds of protein. When you make
cheese, you can really tell that there's
two kinds of protein because when you
make cheese, they separate, right? So,
you have the clear uh more watery kind
of protein that they used to throw away.
Now, they make protein powder out of it.
So, it's called whey. So, when you go to
the gym, they tell you to take your
protein and you put it as powder in your
shake or whatever. That's whey. And then
the other stuff that they make the
cheese out of. So it so cheese is like
concentrated caffeine. It really is what
it is. But casein is 87% of cow's
milk. And it promoted according this is
a quote from the book you guys. It
promoted all do you see the word right
there? All stages as in like one, two,
and three. Yeah. Kurds and way. Thank
you very much. Thank you. Yes. Curds is
the casein and whey is the clear
liquid. So casein makes up 87% of cow's
milk protein and promoted all stages
one, two, and three. Initiation,
promotion, and progression of cancer
process.
Yikes. I don't know about you. I don't I
I don't want any of the stages. I don't
know about you. I'm just telling you
guys. I'm just telling you guys. All
right. Well, what I want to highlight
here is that it seemed to especially
affect this
one
because all the
mice, all the
rats were given an initiator.
All the rats were infected with the
virus that causes the liver cancer. The
the mice, the rats, they had all been
exposed to aphlotoxin, which is very
very toxic, extremely toxic. You don't
want to have that stuff. And yet not all
them not all of them developed the
cancer. So they had had all been exposed
to number one. And yet something stopped
number
two. Something stopped.
Hm. So anyway, today's topic is causes.
So what are some of the potential
substances do you think that might be in
food other than casein? Because we
already Okay, we saw not casein is
potentially one thing that might
cause cancer. Are there others? Do you
think? What do you think? Yes. Animal
protein. We already said, right? animal
protein. Let me mention some other ones.
Not that I really want to depress you or
anything. By the way, we're not going to
cover all the topic of cancer today.
Okay.
Today, well, here's the thing. It might
be a little bit of bad
news, but as you saw, it's not that bad
news because some of these things might
be initiators, if you will.
But you see how there's a silver lining.
We kind of saw, right? There's a silver
lining there because all of these things
might cause cancer. Okay? Some of these
things I'm going to tell you might be
like at the end you might say, "But what
am I gonna
eat?" Next week I'm going to talk about
not next week. Sorry, sorry, sorry. I'm
I'm doing it every two weeks because on
Tuesdays I also do a presentations at at
the church. Um, but two weeks from today
I'm going to talk
about foods that fight cancer. So that's
the good news. Okay. And also, you kind
of saw a little bit how even if you're
exposed to things. So, some people tell
me, "Oh, but uh foods nowadays, they
have chemicals and they have fertilizers
and they have, you know, all these
things, even fruits." No, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no. Don't think like
that. I I'll tell you I'll tell you why.
I'll tell you why. Don't think like
that. Okay? And you saw a little bit how
Wait, wait a minute. Even if you're
exposed to things like aphletoxin does
not mean you're gonna get cancer. All
right? So please don't think you're
going to just get bad news today. That's
what I'm trying to say. All right? So
but still we need to know what are we
being exposed to? Should we avoid these
things? Hm. Because we don't have to be
putting stuff on our
bodies all the time that are causing
cancer. That's like not a good thing.
All
right. What are the potential substances
that we are exposed to that we should
not be exposed to
unnecessarily? Let's talk about that. We
already said number one, animal protein.
But what in animal protein exactly?
Well, I'll tell you what. This is one of
the theories. There is
a hormone that goes up when we consume
high amounts of animal proteins. So this
is right now like the working theory or
one of the theories of why consuming
high amounts of animal protein because
by the way if you read the book
literally just look at the book and
inside of the book he says that the they
repeated this exact thing that I showed
you with the animal protein the casein
they repeated it with
gluten which is the protein in wheat.
They did not they did could not repeat
the exact results. In other words,
gluten did not
cause what we saw with casein. They
repeated it with soy protein and it did
not cause the same results as with
animal protein. So they tried to imitate
what they saw with animal protein with
plant proteins and it did not do that.
only animal proteins cause that result
that we just saw. Why?
Well, one of the things they think is
because animal protein, not plant
protein, animal protein, elevates a
hormone
called insulin like growth factor
one, otherwise known as
IGF1, which is a growth hormone.
Let me ask you this. When you're a
child, you're growing, right? You're
growing. You're growing. So, you need
some growth hormone for that. But when
you reach your adult height, let's say
at the age, I don't know, 18, 20, maybe
20 to Okay, let's say you you reach the
age of
25. Do you need more growth hormone?
Like a
lot. Do you need a lot of growth hormone
in your
body? What do you think?
Do you need a lot of
it? Probably not, right? What do you
think happens if you're exposed to a lot
of growth hormone
unnecessarily? What starts to
grow? What do you think might grow? If
you have a lot of growth hormone, well,
guess what? You know what
grows right
here? Cancer. No, thank you, Courtney.
You don't need it. When we have excess
growth hormone in our body and we do not
need it, guess what starts to grow?
We're feeding the growth of
[Music]
cancer. That's what happens. So in this
study what they found is people who eat
a low protein
diet that was associated with a
reduction of insulin like growth factor
one which then in turn was associated
with a reduction in
cancer and a reduction in overall
mortality. You see what I'm saying? low
protein, low cancer, low
mortality. Would you like that in your
life? Just a
question. And what they found, this is
just some detail here, is that in people
who are ages 50 because obviously they
did that with older people because those
are people who tend to have higher
mortality and also higher risk of
cancer. is that if people at those uh
ages what they have is higher risk of
cancer. So when you have actually maybe
I can make this bigger. Okay, here we
go.
Um
fourfold increase of cancer if you have
high protein diet.
Fourfold increase of cancer if you have
and increase of mortality. By the way,
today we're not talking about diabetes,
but by the way, people who have diabetes
usually get a high protein diet as a
recommendation or at least low
carb. And this incidentally, this uh
study found a fivefold increase
mortality from
diabetes.
Yikes. if you eat high protein. Who
wants that? I don't know. Not me.
Anyway, so that's what happens. Of
course, I could be talking about this
all day long, but it says right here,
insulin resistance. You guys remember
what we talked about two weeks ago. Hope
I hope some of you were there two weeks
ago, but we talked about insulin
resistance. We're talking about here
insulin like growth factor. Insulin
resistance. Also, I don't know if you
remember when we talked about all the
different complications. We showed a
circle with all the different
complications of insulin resistant
cancer was there. We didn't have time to
talk about
it, but now we can mention what happens.
It just so happens that
insulin, not just insulin like growth
factor, but it says right here, I don't
know if you could see it. This is so
small but it is hyperinsulinemia meaning
a lot of insulin in your body is a
hallmark of insulin
resistance and the increase in increase
of
bioavailable insulin like growth factor
appear to have a
role in tumor
initiation. Who wants that? Not
me. We don't want
that. So, we want to avoid diabetes,
pre-diabetes, because diabetes is the
risk factor for breast
cancer. So, what we eat does matter.
Yes, it does. Now, there's another thing
that I wanted to talk real quick because
it's kind of related to
diabetes. You know how people who have
diabetes, I don't know if you know, but
I work with diabetics a lot. We tell
people who have diabetes, don't walk
barefoot, for instance, in your house.
don't walk barefoot. Why? Because you
can stop on a piece of glass and not
feel it. They tend to have
um they tend to have damage in their
nerves sometimes and they don't feel
when they step on something and they can
get injured and then they get uh
infections in their feet and they don't
realize. And those infections, I don't
know if you know this, they take a long
time to heal. Why? Why do they take a
long time to heal? Because people with
diabetes have lower
immunity. We saw this during COVID. By
the way, why did diabetics have a higher
risk for uh disease and mortality during
COVID? It's because of the lower
immunity. What about
cancer? Is the immune system related to
cancer? That's another uh interesting
thing to think about. So is our
immunity. Should we be thinking about
our immune system? I have a whole
different presentation on that. Maybe
someday I'll do it. How do we keep our
immune system through food, through our
lifestyle, exercise,
uh sunlight,
water, so that we can be fighting cancer
through good immunity. But also
diabetes, preventing diabetes. Because
if we have high blood sugar, the sugar
in our blood constantly high that lowers
our immunity and that's another way
where we can
be our immune system is not fighting
those cancer cells. The same the same uh
cells in our immune system that fight
viruses and bacteria are the same ones
that fight cancer cells. That's what I'm
trying to say. So that's another thing
that I wanted to mention real quick. So
that's what we're talking about when it
comes to diabetes and the immune system.
We have high risk for infections, immune
problems, but also cancer. Okay. So I
just wanted to mention
parenthesis. All right. Okay. Next
thing. This is according to the
International Agency for Research on
Cancer. I didn't make this up. I did not
make this up. This is not me. But
according to
international
agencies, respect to
cancer, processed meats, I don't know if
you know this, processed meat is
considered a
carinogen. Class one, what does that
mean? Class one is the same
uh category as cigarettes. Did you
know tobacco and cigarettes are class
one
carcinogen? In other word is absolutely
100% known that it the likelihood of
causing cancer is
high. And what is processed meats?
Sausages, hot dogs, bacons. You You
probably don't eat that.
Hopefully. I hope you I hope you don't
eat
bacon. You don't, right? Okay. Well,
what about I don't know. Chicken hot
dogs. You know, I I don't think I'm
exaggerating. You tell me if you think
I'm exaggerating. Okay. I don't think
I'm exaggerating when I
say that eating a hot dog is the
equivalent of smoking a cigarette.
What do you
think? I mean, I'm just stating a a
fact. If hot dogs are the same level as
cigarettes, according
to the International Agency for Research
on Cancer, wouldn't you agree that
eating a hot dog is the same thing as
smoking a
cigarette? I'm just
saying. Please don't get offended. I'm
just saying. All right.
uh red meat is 2A. So that's a little
lower
classification. But the thing is we eat
a ton more of red meat. So like 50,000
people die every year they think from
eating red meat cons compared to 30,000
people die every year from eating
processed meat. So actually more people
eat from red meat eat uh die from eating
red meat than die from eating processed
meat because a lot more is eaten of red
meat. That's the thing. So they're both
carcinogenic unfortunate unfortunately
for those who eat it. I haven't had it
in years. But why? Why? Well, there's a
lot of things in meat that might be uh
contributing. So,
uh I don't know. There's a lot of things
that could be doing it, but there's
definitely I'm just going to show you. I
mean, I'm just going to go through these
quickly because there's so much uh
science on this. you I can be boring you
with too many studies but for instance
this one says red meat intake and risk
for breast cancer among premenopausal
women in other words younger women
um so let me see hold on one second
there's one there's another one that
says adolescent so young girls
um at young ages in other words you can
start to
increase the risk for cancer. This is
cancer, by the way. One day I might do
my presentation on heart
disease and what pediatricians say about
when the risk for heart disease starts
might blow your mind. I don't want to
say it now, but it's pretty darn young.
It's very
young. So anyway, uh so adolescent,
yeah, the risk it starts with in
adolescence. That's the pro. That's the
bottom line. Um, this
Oh, okay. I don't want to spoil your
Fourth of July or anything,
but this one talks about grilling the
meat. So, there is
a there is a chemical that is formed
when you put meat on a grill. So, not
only does the red meat have, you know,
the protein and the fat and the
cholesterol, those are things inherent
in the meat, right? But when you put the
meat on the
grill, the fact that you're grilling it
causes the
production of these polyyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons, which are chemicals
basically that are
formed. And there's one for instance
just going to give there's actually a
lot of them that are formed but there's
one I'm just going to give you an
example of one that's called
benzopyrene and just they're mentioned
here you know effects of grilling blah
blah blah if you want to look it up and
read it and all these technical
terms but I'm just going to give you the
equivalent okay so example benzopyrene
okay if grill 2 lbs of
meat, it's the equivalent of 600
cigarettes basically of benzo pyrene and
2 lb of grilled
meat equals 600 cigarettes.
FYI. So maybe grilled
corn or zucchini,
potatoes, maybe.
Don't be mad at the messenger. I'm just
a messenger. Okay. Um I'm just letting
you know. So it's for your good. Okay.
Um
Okay. So moving forward. Okay. There we
go. By the way, they did research in
Australia, you guys, on skin cancer.
Mercy. I know. Um research in Australia.
You think you would think that skin
cancer only comes from the sun, you
know, being exposed to the sun too long,
but yet they found that actually meat
eating contributes to it. So, eating too
much meat actually does uh contribute to
skin cancer as well. Okay, I'm just
going to mention a couple more things.
All right, and then I'll give you the
good news. Acryomide. Yikes.
What in the world is
acryumide? It's formed when we cook
foods at high
temperatures like for instance frying
because frying is when you really
achieve the very very very high
temperatures especially starchy
foods. Those are the ones that really
produce a lot of acryummites.
You know what I mean when I say starchy
foods?
Potatoes,
tortillas. So like, can you think of
starchy foods that are fried that
might have
acryites? Can you think of an example of
a starchy food that is
fried? Can you think of something?
Well, yeah. I don't want to give you bad
news, but um this study for instance
says consumption of deep fried
foods. So like French fries, French
fries and potato chips. Okay, I didn't
want to say it, but okay, here it is.
French fries and potato chips are like
the number one source of acryammites.
But honestly, anything that has a
batter, you know, things that have like,
you know, like these things,
uh, cause not just, this is just one
example, okay, I'm just saying prostate
cancer as an example, but acryomides are
be have been, um, have been found to
elevate Yeah, French fries. Thank you
guys. Fried rice
probably. Yeah. all starchy foods, foods
that have carbohydrates, honestly that
are
fried. Yikes. Sorry you guys. I didn't
want to give you so many bad news, but I
just want you to know so that when it's
better to know not to know, I think
so. Here are some of the if you want to
have the the um the original research,
you have it. Okay, I I want you to know
that I'm not making it up. So, I'll
you'll have um access to the PDF if you
want to have the the
the research where it shows. Okay, I'm
not making it up. So, so that you know
in case you also want to do these
presentations, you're welcome to use my
um my slides for sure. Okay, last one. I
think I think
TMAO. What is TMAO?
trimethylamine and
oxide. What is that? It's a compound
produced by gut
bacteria that can be linked to increased
risk of heart disease, stroke, and other
cardiovascular events and cancer
unfortunately. But it's not just with
any food that this is produced in the
gut. Certain foods produce this
particular compound.
uh foods that contain
Lcarnitine, choline, lecithin, and high
amounts. And these happen to be
mostly animal foods. And when they are
in the colon, when they interact with
the gut bacteria, they produce certain
metabolites converted by the enzyme by
enzymes in the human liver that then
promote that that then actually become
TMAO and then promote
inflammation and cause diseases such as
heart disease, strokes
and cancer.
So this T
TMAO promotes cell proliferation uh
proliferation. Andogrogenesis means that
the cancer gets all these blood vessels.
So it gets fed with blood
vessels. You don't want that. You don't
want that. So colurectal cancer
obviously because it's the where the
where this is being produced a lot of.
So uh so here's another one. It's
talking about the relationship between
the intestinal microbiota. So that's
what we were talking about right
final. This is the last thing I want to
talk about cholesterol. But watch this
is from the diet. Cholesterol from the
diet because you would not believe the
amount of people that fight me on
cholesterol. People argue on
cholesterol so much especially people
who are on the keto diet.
Keto diet, people love it. Carnivore
diet nowadays, everybody's on the
carnivore diet and people defend it like
I don't know, people just like it's like
a religion. People love their keto diet,
their carnivore diet. And they want to
tell you that cholesterol is the best
thing in the world. I don't know why.
And so they tell you dietary cholesterol
does not elevate serum cholesterol.
Basically, what they're saying is that
you can eat all the cholesterol you
want. It's not going to elevate your LDL
cholesterol. Whatever. I don't care.
Because guess what? Even if it doesn't,
the dietary cholesterol has been found,
in other words, the cholesterol you
eat, hear me out, the cholesterol you
put in your mouth and then you swallow
and then goes into your digestive
system, that cholesterol has been found
to cause cancer. So even if it does not
elevate your blood cholesterol, see what
I'm talking about the difference. The
cholesterol you eat, the foods that have
high cholesterol, even if they don't
elevate the cholesterol in your blood,
which they might not, fine. That comes
from somewhere else. I'll tell you one
day when I do the presentation on heart
disease, that comes from uh saturated
fats, which can be animal or vegetable.
Fine. But the cholesterol you do
eat, and that's only animal product.
There's no such thing as vegetable
cholesterol. That's
different. The cholesterol you eat does
elevate the risk
for, do you see right there? Do you see
it for
cancer? Independent of heart disease.
This has not is not related to heart
disease, you guys. This is independent
of heart
disease. Did you know this, by the
way? I don't think a lot of people know
about this. I really don't think a lot
of people know about this. I think most
people have no
idea. But here it is. Dietary
cholesterol intake and cancer. It's not
just one study. I could be here sitting
for hours and hours showing you studies,
but that would bore you. So, I'm just
going to show you like two or three.
Cholesterol and breast cancer
pathophysiology. Okay. They show you
like how it does
it. And I'm just going to show you maybe
one more. Uh, egg. Oh, well, okay. Eggs
number one source of cholesterol in the
diet, by the way. So, eggs is the number
one. Okay. Obviously, it's the egg yolk.
If you just eat the egg white, it's not
going to have the cholesterol. It's just
protein. But the egg yolk is the number
one source source of cholesterol in the
diet. That's indisputable.
And here's a a study that links egg
consumption with breast cancer. And
there's many of these. There's not just
one. There's many of these. So what I'm
trying to tell you is that there is a
clear connection between cholesterol and
cancer. Dietary cholesterol. Okay. I
want to finish with a good news with
some some semblance of
hope because Dr. T. Colin
Campbell in the book, The China Study,
Page 66, says, hear me out. The results
of these and other studies, the results
of his studies, when he says these, he
says his studies and other studies
though
show that what's the word there? Look at
it.
The results of these and other studies
show
that
what
nutrition
nutrition what we
eat, what we put in our
mouth is more
important in controlling the what you
guys in controlling What's the word?
What's the key
word? Nutrition is more important in
controlling
the promotion. What's promotion again?
What's
promotion? Step number two,
remember
initiation. That's when the cells are
damaged. DNA is damaged by something, a
virus, chemical, radiation, whatever,
something. But then there's number two,
promotion. It has to grow.
That cancerous cell, that damaged cell
has to
replicate. If it doesn't replicate and
that then that those two cells become
four and those four become eight and
those eight become 16 and so on and so
forth. If that doesn't happen, there's
no
tumor. That's
promotion. You see what I'm
saying? Those damaged cells have to
replicate. That's
promotion. If that doesn't happen,
there's no
tumor. There's no cancer.
And look at what it says right here.
It's so incredible. I didn't say it.
Good thing I didn't say it. Says, "The
results of these and other studies show
that nutrition what?" Oh, he's so
incredible. He has guts. He says
nutrition is more important in
controlling the promotion of cancer than
the doses of cancer initiators.
So when you hear someone tells you, "Oh,
everything had causes cancer." No, not
everything causes cancer. No, that's not
true. Yeah, you can eat maybe a apple
that has some, I don't know, pesticides
or whatever.
You can wash that off first of
all, but that
apple does not have a protein that will
promote the growth of your cancer. You
see what I'm
saying? But you eat the cheese
pizza and it does promote the growth of
the cancer. You see the
difference? Now, I'm not going to
generalize that this always happens.
There's there's different
cases. There's different circumstances.
This does not apply 100% of the cases.
We don't
know what other circumstances might be
happening in
everybody. This is applies in maybe a
great percentage of the cases. We don't
know every circumstance. We don't know
what people have been exposed to in
childhood and you know whatever but
according to what we have seen in
epidemiolog epidemiological studies by
the way the reason why the book is
called the China study is not because of
what he found in the lab because the lab
was in
Cornell after what he found in Cornell
he went to
China and he did the China study the
biggest epidemiological cancer study
ever done and I'll tell you about that
next okay next program. But
anyway,
please let's try to really get this
point. It's more important what you eat
than when you're exposed to. That's what
he's saying. It's more important what
you
eat. What are you eating? What are you
putting on your plate? What kind of
protein are you putting on your plate?
Are you eating fried foods?
that kind of thing,
right? Then whether your foods
have fertilizers or
whatever now you can wash them off. Try
to wash them off.
Obviously, there's no need to put
ourselves in more danger than we have
to, but what we eat is more
important, right? All right, I'm going
to finish. Oh, one more quote from Dr.
T. Colin Campbell. I love this quote. It
gives me so much
hope. Cancer promotion
is I didn't say it. I'm so glad I didn't
say it. Cancer promote promotion. This
is what he found in the
lab. Cancer promotion is what, you guys?
What's the word? I didn't say it.
I'm just quoting a
researcher. What's the
word? Reversible.
What? Colin Campbell said
it. Cancer promotion is reversible
according to his studies and human
studies too. By the way, some human
studies depending.
Thank you,
Ari. Depending on
what? On
what? On whether the
initial cancer growth, the
initial. So on whether that initiation
in other words on whether the initial
cancer
growth has
what the correct conditions to
grow that's what
matters. So when you are
exposed, does
that
initiator have the right conditions to
grow in your
body when you were
exposed? Now you might not have control
of that because say you were exposed
when you were a child to radon or
whatever and you were eating bunch of
meat when you were a kid. I don't
know. Maybe you didn't have control when
you were a
kid. But now you do. Maybe.
Hopefully. You
see, that's what matters. So, are you
right now? That's the question. Here's
the question for you guys. I'm going to
leave you with this question.
Are you making the conditions now in
your
body correct for cancer
growth or
not? Are
you? I'll leave you with that
question. I will talk about this uh next
time. I'm going to skip blah blah blah.
Next presentation will be May 27th. I
will talk about foods that fight cancer.
How to make the conditions in your body
not to promote
cancer to fight cancer. What I will show
you some things that will blow your
mind, I think, because they're it's
pretty awesome. But obviously, it's more
than just diet. Diet is just one aspect.
There's a whole lifestyle that we need
to incorporate.
And I might if I have time I'll touch on
some if I have a little bit of time I'm
I'll maybe mention the important of
exercise of rest of sleep and other
things. Uh but it's more than that just
diet. But I just want to leave you with
this verse. It says if you diligently
heed the voice of the Lord your God and
do the thing that is right in his sight
give ear to his commandments and keep
all his statutes. I will put none of
these diseases which I have brought on
the
Egyptians for I am the Lord who heals
you. What a beautiful, beautiful
promise. This is my website help for
today.net. Last week I told you I have a
10day
Daniel challenge, 10day Daniel menu. You
can just go in there healthfor.net. net
download it because I told you last week
you can improve your health in or not
last week last presentation two weeks
ago you can improve your health in only
10 days I see it all the time if you
didn't watch last presentation you can
watch it just go to the channel living
mana online church and you can see what
can be done in 10 days literally you can
improve your health so much so I think I
can maybe take five minutes a couple of
questions If anybody has any questions,
we don't want to keep hear people too
long. Uh but if anybody has a question,
we I can definitely I will definitely uh
give our production team my slides. So
you can definitely have the slides.
Absolutely. Yes. So does anyone have any
question before we finish? Anybody have
any
questions? So yes, you can have our
slides.
[Music]
remove health inputs or health insults.
Yes, absolutely. Remove health insults
and replace with health promoters. I
really love that. Yes, absolutely. Um
and yes, we What about air fryer foods?
Thank you. That's a really good
question. Air fryer foods do not achieve
the high temperatures that you would get
with a with frying in oil. is the oil
that elevates the temperatures much
higher. So with air fryer it's just air
not with not oil the oil elevates the
temperatures much higher than that. Uh
let's see let's see if there's any other
someone asked about oil and air fryer.
Yes. Yes. Yeah we got that. So yes oil
elevates higher uh the temperature is
higher than air. So air fryer is much
better. Now of course you can control
the temperature right? So you can always
do it a higher temperature than lower.
So if you're going to do it a higher
temperature, you do it for a shorter
amount of time. Then you don't want to
do high temperature too high amount of
time. Well, you would burn it actually.
So the the less amount of burning there
is in the food, especially if it's a um
um a starchy food, the less amount of
burning you do, the better. Can you
repeat the website? Yes, it's right
here. You see it right here?
Healthforday.net. It's right here. Hell
for
Today.net. Is it a sin to eat clean
meat? No. No. No. No. No. No. No. No.
No. No. It's not a
sin. Nobody will be saved by what they
eat. Only by the blood of
Jesus. So now, can you improve your
health by leaving it out? Yes. But if
you don't have anything else to eat,
well, you don't want to
starve. Now, if you can avoid it, it's
probably better. That's my
answer. You probably live longer. That's
what the um that's what the research
shows.
So, that's my answer. But nobody will
nobody will be saved by what they eat or
not eat. And it's not a sin to eat it.
That's for sure. That's my answer. Uh is
it true that flesh is acidic? eating
flesh is acidic. So the flesh itself no
it's what you when you eat it the um
your body becomes acidic and that a
hyper acidic diet promotes cancer cell
growth. Yeah I would say yes it is it is
it is kind of true. Um your body becomes
acidic and it's not alkalinic. So you
want to eat more of an alkalinic diet.
Yes. Absolutely. I agree with that. Can
you speak of cohay?
you guys want to get me in
trouble. I do not recommend
uh coconut oil. And the reason why I do
not recommend coconut oil is because
it's the highest
in saturated fat. And saturated fat is
the like coconut oil as far as its
chemical
um and molecular if you were to look at
it you know molecular the the way it's
the molecu the molecules look the
structure of the molecules one day maybe
I'll show you visually so you can see it
but the molecular structure of coconut
oil is the closest to animal
fat literally palm oil and coconut oil
are the closest to animal fat. They're a
grease because at room temperature
they're solid and
so they are the ones who are going to
elevate LDL cholesterol apo B
cholesterol which is kind of LDL
cholesterol total cholesterol the more
the most. Uh if you're going to use any
oil I would use only extra virgin cold
press probably olive oil or anything
like that. Maybe avocado oil, if there's
such a thing like cold press, extra
virgin. You don't want any oil that has
been put through
heat. So only cold press extra virgin.
If you can leave out all
oils, even better. Why? Because oils
don't have fiber. And when you consume
fat without its
fiber, you are not going to be getting
that fiber that helps you to
uh that fiber helps binds to the fat
actually and helps to take out the
cholesterol from your body and the oil
doesn't have it. It's also more
concentrated in calories. So, anyone who
wants to lower their cholesterol and
lose weight and decrease the insulin
resistance is easier if you leave the
oil out. If you use any oil, it's better
not to heat it up at all or any very
little, very tiny little bit. So, I
would use very tiny little bit oil or
none at all. All right. Uh, can you do
you have Spanish? Yes, I have way more
in Spanish than English. I'm gonna be
build building up my English, but I have
way more in English. And it's salute
para punto salute
partocom.com. That's uh my Spanish in my
my YouTube channel. It's got 38,000,
40,000, 41,000, I don't even know. It's
like got lots of videos. So yeah, tons
in Spanish. Um yes. So okay, salmon.
Salmon is I guess it's got more fatty.
It's a fatty fish, so it's got more
omega-3s. But you know where the salmon
gets it? From algae. So if you get the
algae, omega-3, you're getting it from
the
source. And the salmon probably has the
nanoplastics and some of the chemicals
and the water that already, you know,
some of the heavy metals. So just get it
from the I would get it just from the
source algae. That's me. Um all right.
What else? Uh grape seed oil probably
again any oil
coldress and uh extra virgin. Okay.
Production says last question. Coconut
milk better than oil. Yes. And better.
Yeah. It's not as as um it's not as
refined. Coconut cream and coconut milk
is not as refined as the oil. Mercury.
Yes. It's in the water. So it's heavy
metal. It's a heavy metal. So it's in
the water. and the fish almost
everywhere any ocean and all the all the
face of the earth unfortunately you
guys. All right, I'm going to pray and
we'll see you in two weeks. Okay, so I'm
going to pray. Thank you very much for
for being connected today. I really
enjoy doing this as you can tell. Um but
thank you, thank you, thank you, thank
you. God bless you. I'm going uh pray to
finish today's presentation. Okay, let's
pray.
Dear heavenly father, thank you so much
for giving us so much information, so
much wisdom. Thank you for giving us
this wonderful, wonderful, wonderful
health message. Thank you for giving us
guidance on what to eat, how to care for
our bodies,
uh telling us that we have a body temple
and that it is the the temple of the
spirit of your holy spirit. Thank you
for for loving us, for saving us and
help us Lord if we have not taken good
care of our bodies. Forgive us and give
us wisdom to move forward taking proper
care of our bodies and help us not to
just keep this to ourselves but to help
others. There's so many people
suffering, so many people sick in this
world. Help us to be light to others to
take a message of of uh sal of of of
salvation and of healing to other
people. In Jesus name we pray. Amen.
Thank you again.